Guide to the Kay B. Crooker Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Kay B. Crooker Papers
1951-1996
1987-1996
2010-016
Crooker, Kay B., 1933-2012
6.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Crooker’s papers include documents relating to zoning ordinances, city planning minutes, activities of subdivisions, news clippings on development issues, City Council speakers, and organizations such as Citizens for Zoning.
Biographical Information:
Kay B. Crooker was a professional and volunteer advocate for Houston’s quality of life for more than thirty years. Appointed to the City of Houston Planning and Zoning Commission in 1984 and reappointed by five different Mayors, Crooker retired in 2008. As a former president of Scenic Houston (a collection in the Houston History Archives) and board member with The Park People (Houston History Archives), Katy Prairie Conservancy, Buffalo Bayou Partnership, Quality of Life Coalition, and Trees for Houston, Crooker was key in the development of Houston’s Tree and Shrub ordinance. Crooker was a strong advocate for zoning and was active in the most recent, unsuccessful campaign to enact zoning in Houston in 1993.
As a neighborhood activist, Crooker became the first woman to join the Tanglewood Homeowners Association’s board of directors. Then the board elected her president of the board. Subsequently, Crooker founded the Houston Homeowners Association and served for three years as its president.
Crooker expressed her philosophy of activism when she signed on with “1000 Friends of Houston – Houston deserves to be a better place to live.” As a dedicated activist, Crooker worked devotedly to fulfill this claim for Houston’s future. Mrs. Crooker died on August 20, 2012. Her endless contributions and hard work for the city of Houston left a trail of great outcomes and her personal imprint on civic duty.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence; Deeds -- Texas -- Houston; Minutes (administrative records); Speeches (documents)
Topical Term:
City Traffic -- Texas -- Houston; Environmental issues -- Texas -- Houston; Homeowners' associations -- Texas -- Houston; Zoning Boards -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Related Materials:
This is Our Home, It Is Not For Sale Film Collection, 1925-2011
Hana Ginzbarg Papers, 1962-1991
Terry Tarlton Hershey Papers, 1962-2010 (partial collection)
Scenic Houston - Scenic Texas, 1963-2008
Citizens' Environmental Coalition (CEC), 1966-2008
The Park People Records, 1970-2009
Scope and Contents
Crooker’s papers include documents relating to zoning ordinances, city planning minutes, activities of subdivisions, news clippings on development issues, City Council speakers, and organizations such as Citizens for Zoning. Arrangement follows as closely as possible Crooker’s own organizational schema, with adaptations sufficient to facilitate the third-party exploration of the collection. Collection includes approximately 6 linear feet of materials. Materials cover the period from roughly the 1950s to mid-1990s.
Detailed List of Contents
- Houston
  Scope and Contents
  This series covers issues in Houston proper and includes materials related to zoning, restrictive covenants, and formation of citizens’ groups such as the Houston Homeowners Association founded by Kay B. Crooker. Information covers the 1950s through 1996. Topics covered include racial issues in deed restricted neighborhoods, community affairs, press coverage, and neighborhood goals to enhance property values and protect homeowners’ rights.
  - Deed restrictions
    - Restrictive Covenants-Lawsuit, Racial Issues, Claims, and Examples, 1951-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Community Affairs Issues, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Modification and Creation of Restrictive Covenants, 1955-1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - News-clippings, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Houston Homeowners Association
    - Mission Minutes and By-Laws, 1984-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meeting Minutes and By-Laws, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Residential Deed Restrictions, Requirements and Forms, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ordinances
    - Billboard Regulations and Backgrounds, 1985-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ordinance for Deed Restriction Amendments, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ordinance for Historic Preservation, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Helicopter Landing Sites (1 of 2), 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Helicopter Landing Sites (2 of 2), 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sanitary Sewer System, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Trees and Shrubs Amendment and Proposals, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ordinances – Development Committee for Community Goals and Standards
    - Controls and Standards - City Planning Files, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Controls and Standards Land Use Plan Research - City Planning Files, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - News-clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ordinances – Off-Street Parking
    - Controls and Standards- Land Use Plan Research - City Planning Files, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Summaries, Brochures and Photos, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Responses to Parking Comments, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ordinance Draft: Construction for Off-Street Parking and Loading, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 26 Amendments, 1955-1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Texas Land Use Law Seminar, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Committee Meeting Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Committee Roster, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Remarks to Council Members, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Comments and Positions, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Houston Parking Study, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Parking Party Invitations, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Congratulation Cards and Letters, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - News-clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Background and Research – Other Cities and States, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ordinances – Private Streets
    - Committee Meeting Minutes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Private Streets for Residential Developments, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Sample Subdivisions and Photographs, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Planning
    - City Planning - Land Platting Policy Manual and Annual Report, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - City Planning Commission Meeting Minutes: Plats Recommendations for Final Approval (1 of 2), 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - City Planning Commission Meeting Minutes, Staff Reports and Policy, 1983-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - City Planning Commission Meeting Minutes: Planning and Zoning Commission (2 of 2), 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Comprehensive Plan, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Planning and Development Department – Goodman Report, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Planning Commission Journal Publication, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Planning Commission Membership and Appointments, 1984-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Planning and Development Department – Newsletters and Fiscal Year Reports, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Planning Commission – Legal Guidelines and Procedures, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Planning Commission Site Tour, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Fault Lines Letter, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Publications, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Planning and Zoning Commission - Controversies, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Background Research and Correspondence: Stub Street Extensions for Major Thoroughfare and Building Setbacks, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Planning Policy Manual, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - News-clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Quality of Life
    - Houston Metropolitan Area Survey (UH & Rice), 1982-1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - News-clippings, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Transportation
    - Metro/Rail Transportation Press Coverage, 1983-1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Metropolitan Transit Authority, Letters of Recommendation, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act (ISTEA), 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Metro Transit System and Traffic Congestion, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Thoroughfare Hierarchy, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Zoning
    - Goals and Policies, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Neighborhood Plan, 1981-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Zoning Background Notes, Presentations, Terms and Conditions, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Ad Hoc Task Force - Issues and Letters, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Land Use Strategy Committee (1 of 2), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Land Use Strategy Committee (2 of 2), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Legal Aspects of Zoning, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - News-clippings, 1980-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Zoning Strategy Committee – Map Corrections, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Leadership Houston Program, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Planning and Zoning Commission Formation, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 48: Code of Ordinances Hearing Draft, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 48: Code of Ordinances Draft, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 48: Code of Ordinances, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Speakers at Council Hearings, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Zoning Strategy Commission Party, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - News-Clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Citizens for a Better Houston, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - History by Meg Madoc-Jones, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Cite Article - No Zoning but Many Zones, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Recommendations on Houston-Style Zoning and Letters, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Planning and Zoning Legal Seminar Draft, 1982-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Pro-zoning Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Zoning Articles News-clippings, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Zoning Supporters Survey Results, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Zoning Performance Standards Policy/Principles Discussion, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Zoning Strategy Committee, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Zoning Background Notes, Presentations Purpose and Functions, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Consultant Team Biographies, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Public Participation Programs, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - User’s Guide and Glossary, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Districts and Strategies, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Houston Home-Owners Association – Pro-zoning, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Land Use Press Coverage, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Preparation for Referendum, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - News-clippings, 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Houston Land Use Regulation Without Zoning, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Research and Collected Information, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Converting Walls to Bridges – Proposed Zoning Ordinance, 1988-1993 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Converting Walls to Bridges – Proposed Zoning Ordinance (Research), 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - City Planning Research, 1981-1991 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Zoning – Citizens for Zoning
    - Citizens for Zoning – Correspondence, Comments and Directory, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Research, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Citizens for Zoning - Handouts at Regional Meeting, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Background Notes, Presentations and Recordings (1 of 2), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Background Notes and Presentations (2 of 2), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Research, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Handouts, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Citizens for Zoning – Press Relations, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Article - “Houston Needs Zoning … It Works”, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Contributions and Expenses, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - News and Information after 11/2 Election, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - List of Supporters and Directory, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Endorsements, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Neighborhood Center, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Budgets, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Speakers Schedule, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Related Materials on Anti-zoning, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Mailing List, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - News-Clippings, 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Pro-zoning Tabloids, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Zoning – Neighborhood Goals for Zoning
    - Steering Committee Members and Goals, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Community Workshops Schedules, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Critical Issues for the Development of Houston’s Zoning Ordinance, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Workshop Summaries, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Zoning – Neighborhood Initiatives
    - Land Use Strategy Committee, Mission III, Public Workshop, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Initiative Recommendations Report, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Neighborhood Initiatives Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Sub-Divisions/Neighborhood/Associations
  Series 2 covers specific neighborhood areas inside and outside Houston and the organizations that evolved to protect and develop those areas.
  - Allen’s Landing Plan, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Braesbrook Landing, Colonnade Street Issue, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Briargrove, Letters and Regarding, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Broad Oaks and Cinco Ranch, Maps of Subdivision, 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Harrisburg-Wayside, Association for the Advancement of Mexican Americans (AAMA), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Hickory Ridge Plat Revision, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Highland Village/Houck, Tenant’s Directory, Undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Heights’s Neighborhood, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Lamar Terrace, Reinvestment Zone, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Neighborhood Meetings, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Neighborhood News-clippings, 1993-1996 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Neighborhood Concerns, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Neighborhood Traffic Project, 1993-1996 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Four Post Oak Port Brochure, Undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - St. George Place, Off-Street Parking /Reinvestment Zone, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - South Main Center Association, Annual Report, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Tanglewood Issues and Oppositions, 1971-1981 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Tanglewood Widening of Chimney Rock, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Tanglewood Correspondence to Neighbors, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Texas Medical Center Background Information, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Texas Medical Center Correspondence Regarding Off-Street Parking, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Texas Medical Center Off-Street Parking Proposal/Exemption, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Texas Medical Center Project/M. D. Anderson, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Information Manual and Financial Statements, 1967-1978 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Traffic Cut-through Neighborhoods, Annual Report, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Uptown Houston, Association Scenic District, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Washington Avenue Coalition, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Waugh/I-45/Allen Parkway/Peden, Founders Park, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - West Oaks II Civic Association and HHA, Replat Laws and Proposed Bill, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Woodlands/Cypresswood, Planning and Zoning Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Urban and Environmental Issues
  Series 3 includes information on environmental issues that affect urban development and quality of life.
  - Environmental Protection
    - Wetlands Research and News, 1979-1996 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Newsletter Submission, 1983-1993 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Bayous and Coastal Subsidence District, 1983-1996 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Forestry Bill, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Flooding
    - Surface Water Run-Off, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - News-Clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Crooker’s Remarks to the President’s Commission on Housing, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Storm Water Management, 1981-1994 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Waterways Planning and Protection, 1984-1996 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Conference on Urbanization and Rivers, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Quality of Life
    - Minimum Urban Rehabilitation Standards, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Materials Regarding Gun Control, 1991-1996 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Affordable Housing, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Elections and Term Limits, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Official Term Limitation, 1991-1996 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Land & Real Estate Deals Affecting Divisions, News and clippings, 1981-1995 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Public/Private Partnership, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Public Policy, Regional Issues Research, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Public Art, Art League of Houston, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Other Cities/States
  Series 4 includes city planning and park preservation materials that Kay B. Crooker collected for research purposes and for examples of effective and progressive policies.
  - Austin, TX Barton Springs Watershed, 1991-1994 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Charlotte-Mecklenburg, Charlotte City Planning Seminars, 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Denver, Colorado, Bayou Coalition and River Information, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Dallas/Oregon, Legal Cases Regarding Zoning, 1992-1996 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Florida/Maryland, Architecture and Planning, Undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Oregon, Property Rights/Takings, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Oregon/Texas/Boston, Park Systems across the Nation, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Zoning News, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 42)